In the last module we saw that number
theory can be useful for key exchange.
上节我们学过数论对密钥交换是非常有用的
In this modlule we will review some basic facts
of number theory that will help us build
而本节我们会复习对构建公钥系统有用的一些
many public key systems next week. As we
go through the material in this module it
基础知识 当我们学习本节的材料时
might help to pause the video from time to
time to make sure all the examples are clear
时不时地暂停本视频可能对更好地学习例子有帮助
So as I said we're gonna use number
theory to build key exchange protocols.
前面说过 数论有助于构建密钥交换协议
We're gonna use number theory to build
digital signatures, public encryption and many, many other things.
所以可以利用数论构建数字签名 公钥加密和许多其它的应用
But before we can
do all that, we have to review some basic
但首先我们必须复习一些数论的
facts from number theory and in fact in
this module we're gonna do a quick course
基础知识 而且本节将会对相关的概念做简单讲解
on the relevant concept. If you'd like to
review some of the material discussed in
但如果你想要课下复习本节讨论的知识
this module offline, I referenced at the
end of the module a free textbook by
我会在本节最后介绍一本由Victor Shoup所著的免费教科书
Victor Shoup and I pointed to some
specific chapters in his book that will
并且我会标出这本书中一些特别的章节 这样可能会
explain the materials that we will cover
here. So from here on I'm going to use the
更好地说明本节所讲的知识  从这里开始我会使用
following notation. I'm going to use
capital N to always denote a positive
一些符号 首先使用大写N标记一个正整数
integer, and I'm going to use lower case p
to always denote a positive prime number.
然后使用小写p标记一正素数
Now I'd like to introduce the following
notation, there's this funny Z that's
此外我还要介绍接下来的这个Z符号
written like two diagonal lines here with
a subscript N I'm gonna use that to denote
它写作两条对角线并附带一个下标N 我用它来表示
the sets as zero, one, two, up to N minus
one. This is actually a very common
由0-（N-1）的一组数 它在密码学中是非常
notation that's used in Crypto, and so
I'll stick to that here. So again, Z sub N
常见的符号 所以忠于密码学中的表示 再次强调
denotes the set of integers 0,1 up to N-1. And in fact, this is not just a
Z带下标N表示一组由0-（N-1）的整数 但事实上 它不仅仅表示
set of integers. We can do addition and
multiplication in this set as long as we
一组整数 还可以在这组整数中做加法与乘法 只要
always multiply module of the number N.
For those of you who know a little bit of
我们乘以模数N 而对于了解一点代数的同学
algebra, I'll just say that Z sub N
denotes a ring where addition and
Z带下标N可以代表乘法与加法均在
multiplication are done modulo N. This is
very common notation in crypto, although
模N条件下的环 这是个在密码学中非常常见的符号
in modern mathematics Z sub N sometimes
denotes something else. But as I said I'm
但现代数学中Z带下标N有时表示其它的东西 但出于忠于密码学的表示
gonna keep on using Z sub N to denote the
set of integers 0 to N-1 with
这里Z带下标N表示加法与乘法均在模N条件下的
addition and multiplication modulo N. So
I want to make sure everybody's
由0-（N-1）的整数组 所以我需要每个人
comfortable with modular arithmetic. And
so let's just look at the number, say, N=12
都熟悉模运算 这里举个例子 假设N=12
And let's just see some basic facts about modular arithmetic. So
然后通过该例了解模运算的基础知识
I'm gonna say that nine plus eight is
seventeen; seventeen is five modulo
首先9+8=17 而17≡5 mod 12
twelve, so I'm gonna write that nine plus
eight is equal to five in Z 12. Now
所以这里表示为Z12中9+8=5
can someone tell me how much is five times
seven in Z12? In other words, how much is modular 12?
然后有人可以告诉我在Z12中5*7等于多少？ 换言之 5*7模12等于多少？
Well, five times seven is 35. And if you recall, 36 is divisible by 12
当然5*7=35 而36可被12整除
So five times seven is really -1 module of 12. 35 is minus
所以5*7≡-1mod 12 且35等于-1模12
one module of twelve. But minus one module
of 12 is basically the same as 11,
但-1模12与11相同
cuz I just add 12  to -1 and I
get 11. And the next question is, how
因为12+（-1）=11 接下来的问题是
much is 5 - 7 seven in the Z12?
Well, 5-7 is -2.
Z12中5-7等于多少？ 当然5-7=-2
-2 modulo 12, well, I just add 12
to -2 and I get 10. As a result,
而-2 mod 12 当然只需在-2上加12 得到10 所以
we say that 5 - 7 is equal to
10. So again, this is just to make sure
结果就是 5-7≡10 mod 12 上面这个例子只是为了确保
everybody is comfortable with this notation of working
in Z12. In other words, working in modulo 12.
每位同学都熟悉Z12中的符号 换言之 就是模12运算
Now, I'd just like to make a
general statement that, in fact,
现在 有一点需要注意
arithmetic in ZN, in other words,
arithmetic modulo N works just as you
ZN中的运算 换言之 就是模N运算的运算方法与你们以前学过的一样
would expect. So, for example, all the
laws that you know about addition and
例如 你们了解的加法乘法法则
multiplication work equally well in ZN.
For example, the distributive law, X times
同样适用于ZN 如 分配律 X*（Y+Z）
Y plus Z, is still gonna be equal to X
times Y plus X times Z. So many of the
同样等于X*Y+X*Z 所以你们
things that you know about arithmetic when
working over the integers or in the reals,
了解的很多整数 实数中的运算法则
will translate to working in, ZN, namely
working modulo N.
都可以转化成ZN中的运算 也就是模N运算
So the next concept we need is what's called a greatest common
divisor, or a GCD. And so suppose they
然后接下来的概念是最大公约数 即GCD 假设
give you two integers X and Y. We say that
the GCD of X and Y is basically the
给定整数X与Y X与Y的最大公约数就是
greatest common divisor it's the largest
number, the largest integer that divides
公约数的最大值 就是能够整除X与Y的最大整值
both X and Y. So for example, what is the
GCD of 12 and 18?
例如 12与18的最大公约数是？
Well the GCD is 6, because 6 divides both 12
and 18,
当然这个数是6 因为6可以同时被12与18除尽
and it's the largest number that divides both 12 and 18.
而且它是能够被12与18除尽的最大的整数
Now
there is an important fact about GCD's in particular, if I give you two numbers, two
integers X and Y, there will always exist
然后有一个关于GCD的重要特征 如果给定两个整数X与Y 则一定存在
two other integers, I will call them A and
B, such that if I look at a times X + B
另外两个整数 a与b 并且有a*X+b*Y与
times Y what I get is the GCD of X and Y.
In other words the GCD of X and Y is a
所求的X与Y的GCD相同 换言之 X与Y的GCD
linear combination of X and Y using the
integers A and B. So far let us look at a
用整数a与b求得的X与Y的线性组合 让我们看一个例子
simple example, here, let's look at the
GCD from before, so the integers for the
例如前面举过的这个例子 所以要求得GCD所需的整数是
GCD would be 2 times 12 Minus 1
times 18. That's 24 minus 18,
2*12-1*18 也就是24-18
which is equal to 6. So the integers A
and B in this case would be 2 and -1
等于6 所以这里的a与b就是2与-1
But this is just an example, and in
fact, these integers, A and B will exist
这里是举的一个特例 事实上 对任意整数X与Y
for any integers, X and Y. Now not only do
A and B exist, in fact there's a very
都存在整数a与b 而且事实上有一种
simple and efficient algorithm to find
these integers, to find A and B. The
非常简便有效的计算这两个整数a与b的方法
algorithm is what's called the extended
Euclidean algorithm. This is actually one
这个算法叫做扩展Euclid算法 它是
of the prettiest algorithms from ancient
Greek times, due to Euclid of course. I'm
古希腊时期非常好的算法之一 当然由Euclid提出
not gonna show you how this algorithm
works here, I. It's a fairly simple
这里我不会说明该算法的工作方式 它只是个很简单的算法
algorithm. I'll just tell that in fact
given X and Y, this algorithm will find A
但需要说明的是 给定X与Y 该算法会在
and B in time roughly quadratic in the
logarithms of X and Y. We'll come back to
大约计算X与Y的对数的二次方倍的时间内找到a与b
that and discuss the, the performance of
Euclid's algorithm I have a bit more
之后 我们返回到这里并讨论Euclid算法 而且我会补充
detail in just a minute. But, for now all
we need to know is that A and B can
一些细节 但现在我们需要知道是确实有方法可以有效地
actually be found efficiently. Now, if the
GCD of X and Y happens to be 1. In other
找出整数a与b  如果X与Y的GCD值正好是1
words, 1 is the largest integer that
divides both X and Y, then we say that X
换句话说 1是X与Y的公约数中的最大值 那么就称
and Y are relatively prime. For example,
the GCD of three and five, it's not
X与Y互素 例如 gcd(3,5) 不难发现
difficult to see that it hap, that happens
to be 1, Because both 3 and 5 are
这个值正好是1 因为3与5都是素数
prime. The next topic we need to talk
about is modulated inversion. So other
接下来我们要讨论的是模逆运算
than rationals we know what the inverse of
a number is. In other words if I give you
不同于我们知道的有理数的逆 也就是说 如果给定
the number 2 the inverse of 2 is
simply the fraction one half.
一个数2 那么它的逆就是分数1／2
the qestion is what about inverses when we, we
work module N. Well, so the inverse of
而这里的问题如何在模N的条件下找数的逆 这里
an element X in Z N is simply another
element Y in Z N such that X times Y is
ZN中的元素X的逆应该是ZN中另一个元素Y 且X*Y
equal to 1 in Z N. In other words X
times Y is equal to 1 modulo N. And this
在ZN中等于1 换言之 X*Y≡1mod N 那么这个
number Y is denoted by X inverse. And it's
not difficult to see that if, if Y exists,
数Y就是X的模逆 不难发现 如果Y存在
then in fact it's unique. And as I said,
we'll use X inverse to denote the inverse
那么它也就是唯一的 这里我们用X＾-1表示X的逆
of X. So let's look at a quick example.
Suppose N is some odd integer, and I ask
举个例子 假设N是奇整数 待求
you what is the inverse of 2 in ZN?
So it's not too difficult to see that the
2在ZN中的逆 不难发现
inverse of two in ZN in fact is N plus one
over 2 and you can see that this is an
2在ZN中的逆应该是N+1／2 不难发现它是一个整数
integer because N is odd, therefore, N+1 is even and, therefore, (N+1)/2
因为N为奇数 因此N+1是偶数 所以(N+1)/2
is in fact an integer and the
range 1..N as required. Now why is (N+1)/2
是整数且在范围1-N中 然后为什么是(N+1)/2
the inverse of two?
Well, let's just multiply the 2 so we do
我们将其乘以2,
2 times (N+1) over 2 and what do
we get? Well, that's simply equal to N+1
计算2乘以(N+1)/2会得到什么？很简单,等于N+1，
and N+1 is simply equal to
1 in ZN. So since their product is equal
而N+1在ZN中等于1。因此，由它们的乘积为1，
to 1. We know that (N+1)/2
is the inverse of 2 in ZN.
得到(N+1)/2是ZN中2的逆。
Now we understand what a modular inverse is, the
question is which elements actually have
现在我们知道了什么是模逆，问题是ZN中哪些元素有逆呢？
an inverse in ZN? And so there's a very
simple lemma that says that if for an
有一个简单的引理表明：若ZN中的一个元素X可逆，
element X in ZN, that element has
an inverse if and only if it is relatively
（条件是）当且仅当
prime to the modulus N, to the number N.
So I'll say that again. X and ZN is
它与模N互质，和N互质。我再说一遍，
invertible if and only if X is relatively
prime to N. And let's quickly prove that.
当且仅当X与N互质时，X和ZN可逆。我们快速地证明一下，
It's actually fairly simple to see. So
suppose a GCD of X and N happens to be
这相当简单。假设X和N的GCD恰好等于1，
equal to one. So X is relatively prime to
N. Well, by this property of GCD as we
即X与N互质。由已知的GCD的性质，
know that there exists integers A and B.
Such that A times X plus B times N is
存在整数A和B，使得A*X+B*N
equal to the GCD of X and N, which happens
to be one. So A times X plus B times N is
等于X和N的GCD，也就是1。所以，A*X+B*N等于1。
equal to 1. Now we can actually take
this equation here and, and us it reduce
现在我们把这个等式记录在这，然后简化它的模N运算。
it's modulo N. So what this means is that
a times X is equal to one in Z, N. Once we
这就是说a*X在ZN中等于1。
reduce this equation modulo N this term
simply falls off because B times N is
最后我们可以把这个取模等式减少这项是因为B*N可以被N整除，
divisible by N and therefore is 0
modulo N. But what we just showed is that
对N取模运算结果为0。我们刚才证明了
in fact X inverse is simply A in ZN. So
because X is relatively prime to N, we
X的逆是ZN中的A。因此，已知X与N互质，
were able to show that X is invertible by
actually building the inverse of X modulo N
可通过求X mod N 的逆证明X是可逆的。
Now what about the other direction?
What happens if the GCD is greater than 1?
换一个方向呢？如果GCD大于1会怎么样？
Then we want to show that there is no
inverse. But that's actually very easy to
我们想证明无逆存在，而这其实很容易证明。
see because in this case, if you claim
that A happens to be the inverse of X
因为在这种情况下，假设A是X模N的逆，
modulo N, well, let's look at ax; aX we know should be equal to 1 modulo N
考察a*x，a*x应该等于 1 mod N，
But if the GCD(X,N) is
bigger than 1, then the GCD(aX,N)
但如果 GCD(X,N)大于1，GCD(a*X,N) 也会大于1。
is bigger than one. But, if the GCD
of A times X and N is bigger than 1,
而如果GCD(a*X,N)大于1，
then it's not possible that AX is
equal to 1. So AX must also be
那么 A*X 就不可能等于1，而是一定比1大。
bigger than 1, and therefore, A cannot
be the inverse of X module N.
因此，A不可能是X mod N 的逆。
So this proves that, in fact, in, when the GCD is
greater than 1, X cannot have an
至此，证明了GCD大于1时，X没有逆。
inverse, because there is no A, such that
A times X is equal to one modulo N
因为不存在A满足A*X等于 1 mod N 。
And this might be a bit confusing, so you
might be best just to, do an example. So
这可能有点令人费解，所以最好举个例子。
let's look at, let's suppose that the GCD
of X and N happens to be equal to 2.
于是，我们假设X和N的GCD恰好是2，
I claim that X is therefore, is not
invertible modular N. Well, why is that
那么，X在ZN中不可逆。为什么呢？
true? Well, for all A, we know that A
times X is gonna be even, is even. And the
我们知道对任意的A，A*X为偶数。
reason we know that is because, well, 2
divides X and 2 divides N. Well, since
因为2能整除X，也能整除N。
two divide X, 2 is also gonna divide A
times X. And therefore, A times X must be
若2能整除X，那么2也能整除A*X，无疑，A*X必是偶数。
even. But what that means is that there's
no way that A times X is equal to 1 modulo N
这说明A*X不可能等于 1 mod N 。
In particular, there's no way
that A times X is equal to B times N + 1
特别地，A*X不可能等于B*（N+1)。
This simply can't happen, this
equality must not hold. Because this side
A*X=B*(N+1)不成立，不然等式两边不相等。因为一边
happens to be even, as we said. B times N
for exactly the same reason is also even:
刚好如我们所说是偶数，同理，B*N也是偶数：
N is divisible by two; therefore B times N
is also divisible by two. So therefore B
N能被2整除，所以B*N也能被2整除，所以
times N+1 is odd. And since even
can't equal to odd, it's not possible that
B*(N+1)是奇数。因为偶数不可能等于奇数，所以
A times X is equal to some multiple of N+1. And in particular this means
A*X与N+1的倍数不相等。这表明：
that A cannot be the inverse of X because
A times X cannot be 1 mod N so X is not
A不可能是X的逆，因为A*X不等于 1 mod N，因此，X在模N情况下
invertible modular N. So now we have a
complete understanding of what are the
不是可逆的。现在我们完全理解了什么是可逆元素。
invertible elements. Basically, we know
that an element is invertible if and only
基本上，我们知道了：当且仅当一个元素与N互质时该元素可逆。
if it's relatively prime to N. And what I
like about this proof is I would say this
这个证明让我喜欢的地方，我愿意称其为
is what's called a computer-science proof
In the sense that not only does it prove
计算机科学证明。从某种意义上说，它不仅证明了
to you that the inverse exists; it also
shows you how to efficiently calculate the
可逆解的存在性，同时证明了如何有效计算逆运算的结果。
inverse. And the way we calculate the
inverse, is basically by using this
而计算逆运算的结果的方法基于
extending decreasing algorithm. Define the
numbers A and B. And once we found the
扩展递减算法。定义数字A和B，一旦我们算出A和B，
numbers A and B, we done because A is the
inverse of X. And the numbers A and B can
计算就完成了，因为A是X的逆，而且可以高效地
be found very efficiently. So along the
way I've also shown you an algorithm for
计算出数字A和B。所以在证明过程中我已经告诉了你们计算
inverting elements, modulo N.
模N的元素的逆的算法。
Okay. So bear with me, and let's introduce this little more notation.
So we're gonna denote by ZN as the set of invertible elements in
OK.坚持一下，再介绍一个符号。我们用ZN*表示ZN中可逆元素的集合。
Z N. In other words, ZN is the set
of all elements in ZN such that GCD(X,N)=1
换句话说，ZN*是ZN中满足GCD(X,N)=1的元素的集合。
Okay. But I want you, again, to think of ZN as
OK.再一次，我希望你们只是把ZN*看成
basically those elements in ZN that have
an inverse. So let's look at a few
ZN中逆存在的元素的集合。下面，我们来看几个例子。
examples. So let's start with a prime p.
We know that of the integers from zero to
首先，质数p。众所周知，所有从0到p-1
p-1, all of them are gonna be
relatively primed to p except one
的整数都和p互质，除了一个
integer--namely, the integer 0. Zero is
not relatively primed to P, because the
整数――0。0和p不互质，因为
GCD(p,0)=0, not 1. So
therefore, if p is a prime, the set ZP
GCD(p,0)=0，不等于1，因此，若p为质数，集合ZP*
is simply ZP minus 0, Which means
that everything in ZP is invertible
就是ZP减去0，也就是说，除0外，ZP中的所有元素都是可逆的。
except for 0. So if you like the size
of ZP, it's simply P-1. Now
如果你想知道ZP*的大小，很简单，就是p-1。接下来，
let's look at our favorite integer again.
So why don't you tell me what is Z12
再看看我们最喜欢的整数。为什么不告诉我Z12，
what is the set of invertible elements modulo 12?
Z12可逆元素的集合是什么？
And the answer, of course, is all the numbers
that are relatively primed to 12--namely,
当然，答案就是所有和12互质的数字，即
1, 5, 7, and 11. So, for
example, 3, 4, 6--all of those are
1,5,7和11。其他数字如3,4,6――他们都不是可逆的
not invertible because they all have a, a
non-trivial GCD with twelve, And as we
因为他们都和12有一个大于1的GCD。
said before, if I give you an element X
and ZN, you can find its inverse
如前所述，给定元素X和ZN，可通过扩展Euclid算法
using the extended Euclidean algorithm.
You can find its inverse very efficiently,
算出X的逆，实际上，用这种算法
in fact, using this algorithm. So what we
just learned is basically how to solve
计算很高效。所以，我们刚才学习的只是怎样解
modular linear equations. In other words,
if I give you a linear equation and I ask
模数线性方程。换句话说，如果给定一个线性方程，
you to solve it mod N, it's actually very
easy to do. All you do is you move B to
求解并对N取模是很简单的：只需要将B移到另一边，
the other side so you have a minus B, and
then you multiply by A inverse. So the
得到-B，然后乘以A的逆。
answer is minus B times A inverse. And you
can find A inverse using the Euclidean
答案就是(-B)*A^(-1),可以利用扩展Euclid算法计算A的逆。
algorithm. And once you have a inverse,
you'd simply multiply it by minus B,
一旦算出了逆，将其乘以-B，
modulo N, and that gives you the solution
to this linear equation. Now the
mod N,就得到了线性方程的解。
Euclidian algorithm actually takes time
that's quadratic in logarithm of N. So it
Euclid算法实际花费时间是N的对数的平方，所以
takes time proportional to log squared N.
And as a result we say that this is a
它花费的时间和logN的平方成比例，因此，我们称这是一个
quadratic algorithm for solving linear
equations, modulo N, and if fact this is
解线性方程的二次算法，mod N，而且，这也是
the best know algorithm. And so if you
think back to your high-school algebra
最广为人知的算法。回想高中代数，
days, after you learned how to solve
linear equations, the next question was,
在学习解线性方程之后，接下来的问题是，
well, what about quadratic equations. And
that problem is actually quite
如何解二次方程。这个问题很有趣，
interesting, and we're gonna see that in
the next few segments.
在接下来的几节，我们来看看怎么解决这个问题。